<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BADNESS 10000</title>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:8080/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link>
    <link>http://localhost:8080</link>
    <description>Exploring the world of software and functional programming, one compile error at a time.</description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
    <generator>Wintersmith - https://github.com/jnordberg/wintersmith</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>A functional solution to Twitter's waterflow problem</title>
      <link>http://localhost:8080/articles/waterflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8080/articles/waterflow/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently came across an interesting problem at &lt;a href=&quot;http://qandwhat.apps.runkite.com/i-failed-a-twitter-interview/&quot;&gt;Michael Kozakov’s
blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some interesting thoughts on the whole software interview
process over there. I don’t have much to add on the subject. However,
I thought the problem presented was quite interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some thought I managed to boil this down to a simple functional
one-liner I though was interesting enough to share. First, let’s take
a look at the problem definition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quoting the original source:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Consider the following picture:”
&lt;img src=&quot;http://qandwhat.apps.runkite.com/content/images/2013/Oct/twitter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Levels&quot; width=&quot;300&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In this picture we have walls of different heights. This picture is
represented by an array of integers, where the value at each index is
the height of the wall. The picture above is represented with an array
as [2,5,1,2,3,4,7,7,6].”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://qandwhat.apps.runkite.com/content/images/2013/Oct/twitter_water.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Filled&quot; width=&quot;300&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now imagine it rains. How much water is going to be accumulated in
puddles between walls?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We count volume in square blocks of 1x1. So in the picture above,
everything to the left of index 1 spills out. Water to the right of
index 7 also spills out. We are left with a puddle between 1 and 6 and
the volume is 10.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How would we go about finding a solution to this problem? I find this
to be especially interesting, as there were many solutions posted to
this problem &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/mkozakov/59af0fd5bddbed1a0399&quot;&gt;over
here&lt;/a&gt;, that
were incorrect. My own immediate intuition led me to a solution that
didn’t cover all cases as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can we analyze this problem such that we can get a solution and
implementation that we can be confident is correct?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach I suggest would be to start with the question: “Given a
block in this graph, when will it be filled with water? We can assume
there will be enough rain to fill any holes as far as is possible, so the
only question is when the water will spill over to the side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, the condition for the water to stay in a given square is that
there is some wall to the &lt;strong&gt;left&lt;/strong&gt; that is higher than the height of the
given square, as well as some wall to the &lt;strong&gt;right&lt;/strong&gt; that is higher that
the height of the given square.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we let \(h_i\) be the height of index \(i\), and let
\(high_i^{left}\) denote the highest point to the left of index
\(i\), and similarly define \(high_i^{right}\) we can express this
as.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sqaure of height \(h_i\), is filled when
\[ h_i &amp;lt;= high_i^{left} \land h_i &amp;lt;= high_i^{right} \]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can simplify the conjunction by expressing this via \(min\)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[ h_i &amp;lt;= min(high_i^{left}, high_i^{right}) \]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can now easily see that the height of the water level of each
index, which we’ll call \(level_i\) can be expressed by turning this
inequality into an equality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[ level_i = min(high_i^{left}, high_i^{right}) \]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leaves us in good shape for actually computing the answer. We
start by calculating the values if \(high\). Starting with \(high_i^{left}\) we note that
this can be expressed as a simple recursive equation in terms of \(h\) and itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[ high_0^{left} = h_0 \]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[ high_{i+1}^{left} = max(h_{i+1} , high_i^{left}) \] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This a recursive relation, where we apply an operator (\(max\)) to
accumulate values in a list (\(h\)). We have a tool in the
functional programming arsenal for computing exactly this, namely
&lt;a href=&quot;http://hackage.haskell.org/package/base-4.6.0.1/docs/Prelude.html#v:scanl1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;scanl1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For e.g. the input &lt;code&gt;h = [2,5,1,2,3,4,7,7,6]&lt;/code&gt; from the original post, we get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;scanl1 max h 
&gt;&gt; [2,5,5,5,5,5,7,7,7]
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly for \( high_{right} \) we have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[ high_n^{right} = h_n \]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[ high_{i-1}^{right} = max(h_{i} , high_i^{left}) \] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we can use &lt;code&gt;scanr1&lt;/code&gt; to compute it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;scanr1 max h 
&gt;&gt; [7,7,7,7,7,7,7,7,6]
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now getting back to \(level\), which, as we recall, was defined as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[ level_i = min(high_i^{left}, high_i^{right}) \]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is easy to compute, we only need to apply a function (\(min\))
element-wise, which we can do via an application of &lt;code&gt;zipWith&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;zipWith min (scanl1 max h) (scanr1 max h)
&gt;&gt; [2,5,5,5,5,5,7,7,6]
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have defined the height of the water level at each index, all
that is left is subtract the height of the “ground”, element-wise, to
get the amount of water contributed at each index.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;let level h =
  zipWith min (scanl1 max h) (scanr1 max h)

zipWith (-) (level h) h
&gt;&gt; [0,0,4,3,2,1,0,0,0]
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now all that remains is taking the sum of the contributions at each
index. This is, of course, as simple as applying the &lt;code&gt;sum&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our complete implementation is now&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;water h = sum $ 
  zipWith (-) 
    (zipWith min (scanl1 max h) (scanr1 max h))
    h

water [2,5,1,2,3,4,7,7,6]
&gt;&gt; 10
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can now be confident that our implementation is correct. The
breakdown of the problem corresponds nicely to our mathematical
analysis, and our code is clean and declarative. The only price we
have to pay is a linear use of extra space (arising from the use of
&lt;code&gt;scanr1&lt;/code&gt;), which is cleverly avoided in &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/mkozakov/59af0fd5bddbed1a0399&quot;&gt;Michael Kozakov’s imperative
solution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>